<page
    name = "admin"
    title = "Administration"
    subtitle = "Look After your Deployment"
    >
<content type = "gurudoc">

Monitoring a Server
*******************

There are several ways to monitor a running OpenAMQ server process:

 1. Using the operating systems' process monitoring tools.

 2. Using the OpenAMQ Console ('amq_shell'), described below.

 3. Using the server's own monitoring output.

The simplest way is to run the server using the --dump_state option,
as follows:

    amq_server --dump_state 5

You can redirect the output to a log file, and monitor the log file.

Using the OpenAMQ Console
*************************

Principles
==========

The amq_shell provides a command-line administration tool for OpenAMQ.
You can use this tool by hand, or automatically in shell scripts.  Normal
OpenAMQ users can view information; super users can also change the server's
state, e.g. killing blocked connections or over-full queues.

Console Command Line
====================

Run this command:

    amq_shell -u !username! -p !password!

These are the command-line options:

    !-s! hostname      Broker hostname and :port (localhost)

If the amq_server is running on a different system and/or non-standard port,
use the -s option to specify the correct !servername:port!.

    !-V! virtualhost   Specify cluster virtual host

You need this when working with servers that are in a cluster configuration.
The cluster virtual host you specify must match that specified in the cluster
configuration.

    !-u! user          User name for console access (guest)

Specify the user name for the connection.

    !-p! password      Password for console access (guest)

Specify the password for the connection.

    !-e! "commands"    Run shell commands, delimited by ;

Specify a list of commands to run, which can be any commands that you may
type when in the amq_shell prompt (see below).

    !-x! filename      Save all status data as XML

Saves all printed data as an XML file, useful if you want to re-process the
data mechanically afterwards.

    !-t! level         Set trace level (default = 0)

Used to debug the communications between the Console and the OpenAMQ server.

    !-b!               Show broker status and then exit

Show a summary of the broker status, without entering the prompt.

    !-r!               Report all active local brokers

Scan the current system for all OpenAMQ brokers running on ports 4096-8192.
Will not attempt to look for brokers above or below that range.

    !-q!               Show all broker queues and exit

Show a summary list of all the broker's queues, without entering the prompt.

    !-c!               Show all broker connections and exit

Show a summary list of all the broker's connections, without entering the prompt.

    !-d!               Show date and time in shell output

Add the date and time to all printed messages.

The Console Prompt
==================

When the Console connects successfully to the default or specified OpenAMQ
server it will display a prompt so that you can enter commands:

    amq_shell/1.2b0 - Management Console for OpenAMQ Brokers
    Copyright (c) 2007 iMatix Corporation

    Connected to OpenAMQ Server/1.2b0 on 62.176.172.196:5672

     broker = "OpenAMQ 1.2b0" 
     Date, time broker started ............. 2007-03-15T12:55+01:00
     Broker is locked? ..................... no
     Memory used for all data .............. 10604K
     Memory used for messages .............. 1K
     Number of queued messages ............. 2
     Number of queue consumers ............. 1
     Number of queue bindings .............. 2
     Number of message exchanges ........... 8 [ls exchange]
     Number of shared queues ............... 0 [ls queue]
     Number of connections ................. 1 [ls connection]
     [shutdown] [lock] [shake]
    /62.176.172.196:5672>

Note that:

 * The available actions are listed in square brackets.  For example when
   you are looking at a broker these are the available actions:

    [shutdown] [lock] [shake]

 * Type 'help' at any prompt to get explanations.  These commands are
   available at all times:

    Command            Has this effect
    -------            -------------------
    ls | dir           Show broker and all children
    nnn                Look at item [nnn] (nnn is a number)
    ?text              Look at item matching text
    /                  Return to broker item
    .                  Refresh current item
    ..                 Move back to previous item
    set name value     Set object property
    help               Show this text
    exit | quit        Leave the OpenAMQ shell

Administration FAQ
******************

 - !What do I need to check for when I manage a server?! Answer: mainly,
   CPU usage and memory consumption.

 - !Does OpenAMQ work with [insert random monitoring tool here]!? Answer:
   it is easy to write scripts to monitor OpenAMQ servers from most
   monitoring tools.

</content>
</page>
