<page name    = "download">
  <language name = "en">
    <title>Download</title>
    <content>
      <h1>Software License</h1>
      <p>
        OpenAMQ is free software licensed under the Apache License, version 2.0.
        You may only use this software in compliance with the License.
      </p>
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li><a href="http://apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">Apache License, version 2.0</a></li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        <h2>Permissions and Limitations</h2>
      </p>
      <p>
        <b>No Warranty</b>
      </p>
      <p>
        Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
        distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
        WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or
        implied.
      </p>
      <h1>Download OpenAMQ</h1>
      <p>
        Current version is 0.8b1.
      </p>
      <p>
        This is a beta release of the server and clients.
      </p>
      <h1>Unix Packages</h1>
      <p/>
      <h2>Source package</h2>
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="http://www.openamq.org/pub/openamq-latest-src.tar.gz">
              openamq-latest-src.tar.gz
            </a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        Unpack into a working directory and run <tt>./configure</tt> and then
        <tt>make</tt>.  The source package includes recent validated versions
        of the Apache Portable Runtime (APR) and the Berkeley Database (BDB) as
        used by OpenAMQ.
      </p>
      <h1>Win32 Packages</h1>
      <p/>
      <h2>Source package</h2>
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="http://www.openamq.org/pub/openamq-latest-src.zip">
              openamq-latest-src.zip
            </a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        Unpack into a working directory and run <tt>configure</tt> and then
        <tt>make</tt>.  The source package includes recent validated versions
        of the Apache Portable Runtime (APR) and the Berkeley Database (BDB) as
        used by OpenAMQ.
      </p>
      <p>
        Requires Microsoft Visual C++ 6.0 or later.
      </p>
      <h2>Binary package</h2>
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="http://www.openamq.org/pub/openamq-latest-win32.zip">
              openamq-latest-win32.zip
            </a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        Download and unzip the package into a target directory.  The
        <tt>clients</tt> subdirectory contains OpenAMQ client tools.  The
        <tt>servers</tt> subdirectory contains the OpenAMQ server binaries.
    </p>
    <h1>Previous versions</h1>
    <p>
    Since the product is still undergoing rapid development, we reccommend that
    you always use the latest version available. New releases happen
    frequently, generally once every other week. If for some reason you require
    an older version of the software, you can find all archived packages 
    <a href="http://www.openamq.org/pub/">here</a>.  
    </p>
    </content>
  </language>
</page>
