<page
    name = "faq"
    title = "FAQ"
    subtitle = "Frequently-asked Questions"
    >
<content type = "gurudoc">

Frequently Asked Questions
**************************

Can I tell other people about AMQ?
==================================

If you have to ask this question, the answer is "no".

What is the status of the OpenAMQ project?
==========================================

Development started in October 2004, and we are currently at a
version 0.8 which implements the core of AMQP.  We plan to review
the AMQP specifications to make the protocol more general, following
the seven months of experience from implementing the server and clients.
This 0.9 protocol specification is planned for mid-May.  The server
and clients will conform to that specification by end-May.  At the
same time we are implementing native multithreading in the server to
achieve our target volumes (100k messages/second) on large boxes.
The 1.0 release has not been specifically planned but should be
ready by October 2005, approximately one year after development of
the software started.

Will OpenAMQ handle 100k messages per second?
=============================================

A lot depends on the type of messages and whether we achieve a
good use of OS threads to spread work out between multiple CPUs.
The matching engine in OpenAMQ can today perform about 2M matches
per second per Ghz. So our bottlenecks will mainly be network i/o,
and disk i/o for persistent messages.

What is special about OpenAMQ?
==============================

It's open source, it's ANSI C, it's fast, and small.  The server
runs in 3-4MB, depending on the size of in-memory queues.

AMQP - the protocol - defines a wire-level standard, so you can
develop your own bridges, clients, and servers that interoperate with
or replace the standard components.

The OpenAMQ clients and server implement industrial-quality
messaging, capable of running in production scenarios.  The software
must still be hardened for stress cases.  But its goal is simple:
to provide an open source commodity middleware that performs at least
as well as, and generally better than, any commercially-available
middleware product.

How can I participate in the OpenAMQ process?
=============================================

You should [/maillist.html:join the amq-dev mailing list]

</content>
</page>
