<page
    name = "features"
    title = "Features"
    subtitle = "Main Features"
    >
<content type = "gurudoc">

OpenAMQ Features
****************

Message Routing
===============

Implements the AMQ message routing architecture with a set of high
performance exchange types:

 - Implements the AMQP fanout, direct, topic and header exchange types.
 - Create and manage exchanges (limited to 64k exchanges per server).
 - Hierarchical topics of any complexity (limited to 128k topics per exchange).

Message Queuing
===============

Implements the AMQ queueing model with flexible user-defined message queues:

 - Create and manage named or unnamed queues (limited to 64k queues per server).
 - Basic content messages of zero bytes up to 4Gb.
 - Multiple readers per queue with round-robin dispatching
 - Asynchonous message publishing and dispatching.
 - Shared queues and exclusive private queues.

Resource Management
===================

Provides the operator with control over use of system resources:

 - Configurable limits on queue sizes.
 - Configurable limits on maximum memory used for messages.
 - Automatic slowing of heavy publishers when limits are exceeded.

Ease of Use
===========

Is designed for extreme usability and configurability:

 - Single stand-alone binary.
 - Natively portable to all modern operating systems.
 - Runs with zero configuration if needed.
 - Configurable through command-line switches.

Clustering and Failover
=======================

Supports failover and scalability through in-built clustering:

 - Create server clusters of any size.
 - Fanout publish/subscribe load across many servers.
 - Configurable client-server heartbeating.
 - Cluster configuration wizard.(*)

Security
========

Supports extensible and configurable security options:

 - Configurable user definitions.
 - SASL authentication (PLAIN mechanism).

Administration
==============

Is easy to administer via secure remote shell or the command line:

 - Configuration via XML configuration files or command-line.
 - Remote administration and configuration (amq_shell).

Logging
=======

Includes a complete log file management system:

 - Configurable debug logging levels.
 - Logging of normal client application accesses.
 - Logging of all exceptional events, warnings, and errors.
 - Automatic daily cycling of log files.
 - Configurable log archiving process (compression, removal, etc.)

WireAPI Client Principal Features
=================================

Provides the cross-language WireAPI for application development:

 - Support for all methods defined in the AMQP standard.
 - Asynchronous background message delivery.
 - Error reporting to applications.
 - Currently available for C and C++.

Automation
==========

Comes with tools for testing and automation:

 - Includes full test client (amq_client).
 - Extensive [/wireml.html:WireML] scripting language for automation and testing.
 - Console extension protocol.

Coming Soon...
==============

Planned and/or in progress:

 - Secure SASL authentication mechanisms.
 - TLS/SSL Encryption.
 - Server access controls (user groups and realms).
 - Persistent messages and transactions.
 - WireAPI clients for Perl, Python, PHP, Ruby, Java.

Technical Features
******************

Code Platform
=============

Built on a high-performance portability framework:

 - Multithreaded ANSI C built on custom client/server frameworks.
 - Portable to Linux, Windows, Solaris, and other Unix systems.
 - Single code base builds both single-threaded and multi-threaded versions.

Performance and Stability
=========================

Designed for fast performance and reliability:

 - Server starts and is ready for connections in one second.
 - Built on a low-latency, high-throughput communications framework.
 - Configurable TCP/IP parameters (timeouts, buffers).
 - Configurable OS footprint (memory, number of threads).
 - Configurable memory managers (including heap caching).
 - Processes 40-50k transient messages per second on single CPU.
 - Processes 200k transient messages per second on multiway box
   ([/performance.html:detailed test results).

Features FAQ
************

 - !What makes OpenAMQ special?! Answer: the one thing that stands out with
   OpenAMQ is the quality of the product.  It's not just software - it's a
   large, smooth-running machine that will work for decades, whatever trends
   come and go.

 - !How does ANSI C compare to Java?! Answer: recent Java runtimes are very
   fast but as someone said, "Java kills your system".  If you are running
   a large Java server in any case, you may prefer an AMQ Java broker.  But
   for software that installs silently and runs without a whisper, you want
   a pure ANSI C solution, and that means OpenAMQ.

 - !I want feature X, how do I get it?'  Answer: if it's supported by the
   AMQP standard, and is not yet in OpenAMQ, ask us.
</content>
</page>
