<page
    name = "imatix"
    title = "About iMatix Corporation"
    subtitle = "Software Engineering is our Business"
    >
<content type = "gurudoc">

Developers of the AMQ Standard
******************************

iMatix Corporation, together with engineers from JPMorganChase,
developed the concepts that make up the AMQ standard, in 2004-5. We
wrote the original standards document and iMatix Corporation was one of
the four original firms that created the AMQP Standard Working Group,
together with JPMorganChase, Red Hat, and IONA.

Company Information
*******************

The imatix.com project website was launched in 1995, and iMatix was
founded as a business by Pieter Hintjens, in Belgium in 1998, building
boutique projects for large firms.

Among its major clients were Heineken (who needed an electronic ordering
and payments system for Nigeria), Manpower (who needed a global
web-based ordering platform), CBR (who needed automation for cement
factories in Belgium), and AirTours (who needed a reservation system
server). iMatix projects are categorised by their quality. For example
the AirTours system was put into operation in 1992 and still runs today,
serving thousands of travel agents around Europe. Manpower use the
UltraSource application built by iMatix, in Europe and Asia.

We even designed and built hardware, designing kiosks for CBR's cement
factory in Ghent, Belgium. These PCs had to run non-stop, in harsh
conditions. We designed the casing, selected all components and built a
custom Linux platform that allowed CBR to plug new kiosks into the
network and instantly start using them. The kiosks were installed in
November 2002 and have worked since without a single reported failure.

But our speciality is software, and specifically high-performance
portable servers, which is why we wrote Xitami, a very popular web
server up to 2000, and why JPMorganChase chose iMatix to develop AMQ
from a concept into a production-quality standard and product.

Model Oriented Programming
**************************

Since 1991, Pieter Hintjens and Jonathan Schultz have developed the
concept of [http://www.imatix.net/mop:"model oriented programming"], or
MOP. MOP is a radical step forwards in software engineering. Using MOP,
a developer does not write source code. He write models and an architect
writes code generators that turn those models into source code.

MOP is not a more complex programming language. It is a way of writing
simpler programming languages, dozens of them, cheaply enough that
whatever new problem we face as programmers and architects, an architect
can invent a new modeling language and write the necessary code
generators to hide a complex expression with a simpler one.

More importantly, the process is cheap enough that an expert can invent,
improve, and discard models almost negligently.  Rather than attempting
to design a perfect model by sheer investment, MOP lets an architect
design a perfect model by evolutive trial and error.

A good example of a MOP model is the AMQ Protocol itself, which iMatix
designed this way. The AMQP design is the third complete design: iMatix
built and threw out two working AMQ implementations in 2004 because they
were not (yet) satisfied with the protocol.

MOP leverages high-volume code generation, based on languages that
iMatix has developed over a long time. The first versions of the iMatix
code generation language, GSL, were built in 1995, and these were based
on code generation concepts developed as long ago as 1985 by Pieter
Hintjens and Leif Svalgaard.

Pieter Hintjens
***************

Pieter Hintjens grew up in Africa, and Scotland, and graduated with
honours in Computer Science from the University of York before moving to
Belgium to do his military service. He worked for five years in the R&D
department of the largest Belgian IT firm at the time (SOBEMAP). Sobemap
became Sema Group, and Pieter Hintjens became a free-lance consultant,
for Sema Group and other firms. He started imatix.com in 1995, and
iMatix Corporation in 1998, with the vision of applying enterprise IT
models to the Internet, which at the time still thought CGI was a big
deal. In 1996 his team built the Xitami web server, based on an
architecture and toolset that set a new standard for building fast,
portable internet servers. He is the main architect and visionary
beind the iMatix approach to technology simplification.

His hobbies include percussion, writing, travelling, sociology, and
political activism in the IT domain. He is currently president of the
[http://www.ffii.org:FFII], an international association that represents
several thousand IT professionals and SMEs in over 20 countries, and
fights for open competition, standards, and copyright. The FFII has been
particularly active and effective in fighting against software patents
in Europe since 2000.

Jonathan Schultz
****************

Jonathan Schultz graduated with honours in Mathematics and Computer
Science from the Australian National University, and with first class
honours in History and Political Science from the University of Western
Australia. He has worked with Pieter Hintjens since 1992, developing
code generation languages and frameworks. In 2003-4 he was the lead
developer in the iMatix STEP project (a secure middleware platform for
unreliable networks). Since 2004 he has been the chief technologist for
OpenAMQ.

His hobbies include rock-climbing, bush-walking, yoga, travelling.
Current affairs, politics, philosophy, and environmental and social
activism.  He is currently completing a doctorate thesis in Political
Science at the University of Western Australia.

</content>
</page>
