<page name = "index">
  <language name = "en">
    <title>Commodity Middleware Working for You</title>
    <content>
      <h1>Welcome</h1>
      <p>
      Welcome to the OpenAMQ website.  OpenAMQ is a commodity middleware platform
      that implements an industry-standard protocol - AMQP - as a high-performance
      server and client API.
      </p>
      <h2>The AMQP Protocol</h2>
      <p>AMQP is a standardised wire-protocol for high-performance message exchange
      between a server and a set of clients.  It supports the standard models of
      point-to-point queuing, publish-subscribe, and file-transfer, in a modern and
      language-independent manner.
      </p>
      <h2>The OpenAMQ Server</h2>
      <p>This is a fast open source implementation of AMQP that runs on all
      modern platforms (Linux, Win32, Solaris, other Unixes).  OpenAMQ is written
      in ANSI C and is highly configurable for specific messaging scenarios or
      memory/performance constraints.  It covers the spectrum from high performance
      in-memory pub-sub (handling tens of thousands of messages per second) to
      highly-reliable file-transfer (guaranteed delivery across falible networks).
      </p>
      <h2>The OpenAMQ Clients</h2>
      <p>Whatever your preferred language, you will find an OpenAMQ library or API
      that gives you seamless access to AMQP services.  Most of the OpenAMQ clients
      use the standard JMS (Java Messaging Services) model, with extensions.  It
      typically takes 1-2 days to start using OpenAMQ in your applications.
      </p>
      <p>Of course, since AMQP is an open standard, you can write your own client
      layers.  The average effort is about 10-20 days.
      </p>
      <h1>Next Steps</h1>
      <p>
      On this website you will find an <a href="overview.html">overview</a> of the
      software, downloadable <a href="download.html">source packages</a>
      and published <a href="technical.html">technical specifications</a>.
      </p>
      <p>
      Use the index at left to jump directly to a section of interest.
      </p>
    </content>
  </language>
</page>
