<page
    name = "library"
    title = "Documentation"
    subtitle = "Documentation"
    >
<content type = "gurudoc">

OpenAMQ Documentation
*********************

 - The WireAPI Specifications -
[/doc_wireapi.txt_flat.html:flat HTML] |
[/doc_wireapi.html:full HTML] |
[/doc_wireapi.pdf:PDF (17 pages)]

Describes a standard API for application developers that wish to use
the AMQP for messaging services in their applications.  WireAPI is a
standard cross-language API that gives developers full access to the
full functionality of the AMQP protocol.

 - OpenAMQ Console Interface
[/doc_console.txt_flat.html:flat HTML] |
[/doc_console.html:full HTML] |
[/doc_console.pdf:PDF (17 pages)]

Defines a standard for remote administration of OpenAMQ servers; the
standard consists of an XML language that defines objects and methods,
and a transport mechanism that is itself built on top of AMQP.

Technical Whitepapers
*********************

 - AMQ Background
[/doc_background.txt_flat.html:flat HTML] |
[/doc_background.html:full HTML] |
[/doc_background.pdf:PDF (29 pages)]

Explains the rationale behind the development of AMQ as an architecture
and AMQP as a new industry standard protocol.  This document is designed
as useful background material for people wishing to understand the AMQP
design.

 - OpenAMQ Concepts and Vision
[/doc_concepts.txt_flat.html:flat HTML] |
[/doc_concepts.html:full HTML] |
[/doc_concepts.pdf:PDF (27 pages)]

A general introduction to the OpenAMQ project, intended for a technical
readership. It explains the basic AMQ concepts, and goes into medium
detail on all significant aspects of the architecture and technology.

 - OpenAMQ Matching
[/doc_matching.txt_flat.html:flat HTML] |
[/doc_matching.html:full HTML] |
[/doc_matching.pdf:PDF (8 pages)]

Describes a matching algorithm that provides all the functionality needed
for topic matching and most of the functionality needed for content-based
routing.

Documentation FAQ
*****************

 - !Do I need this documentation to use OpenAMQ?! Answer: no, everything
   you need is explained on this site.  The documentation here provided
   more detail for people who need it.

</content>
</page>
